one welcome to meditating with John
Parvati
I'm a connoisseur cognitive psychologist
and a cognitive scientist at the
University of Toronto where academically
and scientifically study phenomena like
mindfulness meditation contemplation
related phenomena like Insight flow
mystical experience transformative
experience higher states of
consciousness the cultivation of wisdom
pursuit of enlightenment I've also been
practicing the pasta meditation meta
contemplation Tai Chi Chuan Qigong for
over 29 years and teaching and
professionally for almost 20 years so
welcome
this is a course that has been ongoing
for quite some time now every Monday is
the Dharma day on on Monday I will give
people
I'll teach people an important principle
it builds on previous principles and
practices they'll be usually an
experiential practice we do to get a
deeper understanding of how to apply
that principle and then we sit together
and then there's a Q&A on the remaining
days Tuesdays to Fridays we mentally
meet together for sits and I'll usually
review some of this stuff from the
Dharma day one or two days of the week
and then at the end there's usually a
little bit longer Q&A so welcome to stay
but if you want to catch up look for
links to previous lessons Dharma days
and six in the description for this
video so I mentioned there's a QA if you
could limit your questions to the this
practice that's that would be welcome we
can only consider questions directly
related to the practices I'm teaching
for more broad ranging questions there
is a monthly live stream acute QA that
you can go to and order to try to
present those questions and hopefully
get an answer that you will find helpful
all right
so please make sure that you've got
clothing on your and your posture is
ready to go put your phones on do not
disturb and we will begin when I say
begin begin
you
slowly began to come out to be a
practice as best you can
interpret what you called me to give you
practice you're everyt getting
consciousness and cognition not abuse it
it's a part of your practice so we have
a few questions to answer here today one
from Matthew Creedy
should we have a skillful grasp of each
lesson before moving on to the next or
is it better to progress to completely
complete whole practice and improve each
part over time so this goes to you know
sort of like coaching and learning
theory I would recommend that you don't
have like a completely skillful grasp
like it's like in the Tai Chi classics
it's like drawing a circle freehand it's
gonna be very rough and then you draw
other parts all right and then sort of
go through the course but periodically
do you go back and review and perhaps
you know spend two or three sits just
working on one of the components like
you're your sparring and so for a while
right you practice your jobs or your
blocks or kicks right but then you also
have to practice putting them all
together into combination you have to
practice both the gestalt whole and the
individual parts that you have to keep
moving very fluidly between them so it's
not a matter of either/or you should be
moving on but you should also be
periodically going back in zero and yet
on the components zoom in zoom out
philip m86 NYT is it advisable to apply
meditating on distractions during the
core for when you're setting up the core
for I would recommend that I see your
question and sort of there's a it's hard
to know because it depends on you know
how tense the distractions are I would
say if it's sort of you know mild
destruction don't apply the five factors
enquiring minds and listen and give
priority to establishing the core four
but if it's very
intense distraction then I would
recommend applying the five factors of
inquiring mindfulness angry Slav do you
plan on teaching any meditative
practices outside of sitting like while
walking for example so I mean as I
mentioned I'm in discussion with them
are adjacent about how we're going to go
forward after the course is done the
tenth lessons are done I'm trying to do
that one of the things I am considering
doing is teaching you walking meditation
also some preliminary Chi Chi Chi con
these things are all very much under
consideration right now so that's a very
real possibility going forward calder
Martin Ferguson should we think of
meditating on our distractions as a last
resort or something we should seek to do
often even if we are able to dismiss the
distractions I'm gonna turn to the
breath so it's very important that you
don't seek out your distractions if when
you note your distraction it just
disappears that return to your breath so
the five factors of inquiring
mindfulness is when you've got you know
again I'm not in your head and right
everybody's experienced inside their
mind is different of course
at least I presuppose that's the case
and so it's only when the distraction is
quick binding when it's really grabby
when it's really catchy that it's
probably best so when you stand back and
label it and there's still a way in
which you fill that bit of its magnetism
it's attraction that's when it's best to
apply the five factors of implying
mindfulness definitely do not go seeking
for distractions definitely do not go
seeking for options all right so we try
to end very a little bit earlier on
Thursday because I would like to thank
you all for joining I hope it is my
sincere hope that you are finding this
helpful and beneficial there's a lot of
challenges being placed on us right now
on our bodies and minds a lot of there's
a lot of things to contribute some very
maladaptive responses I
hope I'm really genuinely hope that this
is helping I want to thank my good
friend and techno major amar my beloved
son Jason for their continual help
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video you can also
find links to previous lessons previous
6 you can also find access to the
various videos I'm doing voices with
verve Iggy where I'm having discussions
with people who are interested in the
integration between science and
spirituality or awakening from the
meeting crisis you in those videos
you'll find a lot of material unpacking
a lot of the stuff we talked about here
like mindfulness and flow and higher
states of consciousness and wisdom and
enlightenment etc please if you can help
me help others by pointing others to
this meditation course that would be
very helpful to me and it's potentially
helpful to others we will be doing this
every week day not weekends but every
weekday morning at 9:30 est Mondays our
Dharma days Tuesday for Fridays or some
review set every day has a Q&A at the
end for more broader q and A's join the
monthly it's the third Friday of every
month on the monthly Q&A so everyone
please keep practicing the more you Pro
find yourself the stronger this will be
for you the Buddha said in the
Dhammapada there is no enemy worse than
your own wide and there is no ally
greater than your own mind see you all
tomorrow
take good care bye-bye everyone